i call stuart nash thank you very much
mr speaker i rise to support the
insurance
credential supervision bill 2009
the aim of this bill is to reform and
extend the present law relating
to the prudential supervision by the
reserve bank of new zealand the
insurance industry in new zealand
what this bill does mr speaker is
establish a licensing rating for
insurers
and prudential regulations with
compliance largely self-administered
while supervision is provided by the
reserve bank
the bill will cover most entities that
undertake insurance business in new
zealand
including life insurance health insurers
captive insurers
and the insurance activities of
incorporated societies
mr speaker this bill is important to the
people of new zealand for three reasons
for three reasons and a disease that i
will outline and elaborate on
the first is that this bill is another
step
in achieving clear robust laws and
regulations
across the financial sector the second
reason
is it will provide a much higher level
of scrutiny
and security to new zealanders with
exposure
to the insurance industry and the third
reason why this bill is so
important is because it tidies up
legislation
around the sector where there is an
unacceptable level
of uncertainty at the moment
tightening legislation regulating an
important sector of the financial
industry and providing certainty are the
three reasons why labour is supporting
this bill
this will this bill will provide
confidence for all new zealanders
that their parliament is working
together to further
protect their rights and their money
mr speaker we all know that new
zealand's have lost a significant amount
of money
during this economic recession new
zealanders who have worked incredibly
hard
saved hard dreamed aspired and should be
allowed to live
and retire with dignity those dreams
have been taken away
there is an expectation that the courts
will punish accordingly
those that have perpetrated these crimes
but there is also
an expectation that parliament will put
laws in place
that will mitigate the risks of this
type of financial destruction
ever happening again mr speaker within
the new zealand financial industry
the insurance sector was not generally
in distress like other parts of the
sector
of the industry unlike the us where one
of the world's largest insurers aia
went bankrupt with dire consequences for
their financial system the global
financial crisis did however demonstrate
the vulnerability of the sector
as a whole parliament has already
legislated in several areas to tighten
or make laws where there was a real
deficiency in the financial sector
and this is just this bill is just
another step in ensuring that
hard-working kiwis
can have confidence in the sector as a
whole
and this is what i mean when i say that
this bill is another step in achieving
clear
robust laws and regulations across the
financial sector
not only is it sensible but absolutely
necessary in this day and age and it is
why we work together
across parties on this legislation
because for once the national party's
put together
a piece of financial legislation that
actually benefits
all new zealanders the compliance costs
for the industry are not high
and the committee worked hard to ensure
that this bill
would did not provide any level of
competitive advantage to overseas firms
operating in the ninja market
having said that the committee's main
objective was to ensure that the
regulations and rules governing the
industry
provided the level of security
transparency
and accountability that new zealanders
now expect from any sector
in the financial services market
the second reason why i support this
bill mr speaker is because it provides a
much higher level of security to new
zealanders
with exposure to the insurance industry
currently new zealand does not have a
framework
for potential regulation and supervision
of insurers
current insurance legislation is
outdated and inconsistent in its
application
across the diversity of the new zealand
insurance market
this bill requires most insurers to have
a current financial strength rating
that is given by a rating agency
approved by
the new zealand reserve bank there's
been extensive
consultation within the industry around
the provisions of this bill
the select committee considered 57
submissions
and heard 31 oral submissions from a
range of industry and instant
participants
a draft version was released for
consultation well over a year ago
a draft bill reflected policy approvals
by cabinet in december 2007
in august 2008 a labor cabinet
prior to this proposals originated with
the review of financial
products and providers work streaming a
discussion document was released
by med in september 2006 and a further
consultation paper was released by the
reserve bank
in may 2008 this bill mr speaker
had its genesis in the labor party
so what we have ended up with is a bill
that requires all insurers operating in
new zealand market to be licensed
and supervised by the reserve bank and
to comply with minimum
prudential requirements the reserve bank
will have the hour the powers to act and
respective insurers
who are in distress or in other
difficulties
having said that mr speaker in the end
the new regime has been designed around
a self-managing approach
for example insurers are expected to
devise and adhere to their own fit
and proper risk management policies
subject to bank oversight
the cost to the bank associated with the
insurance proposals this is the cost of
reserve bank
it isn't made to be in the range of 2.5
to 4 million dollars per annum
on an ongoing basis once prudential
regulation proposals for insurance have
been fully implemented
excuse me the third reason why i support
this bill
is because it tidies up legislation
where existed an
unacceptable level of uncertainty this
is uncertainty for the industry itself
and uncertainty fraud new zealanders
taking away that uncertainty
is paramount for the new zealand public
to have confidence
in this sector of the financial industry
the compliance costs for the industry
are not high
and the committee worked hard to ensure
that compliance costs were kept to a
minimum
now the main areas covered by this bill
are as follows
licensing of insurers licensing ensures
a consistent set of minimum standards is
met
by all insurers the standards must be
obtained to receive a license
and once a licence is guaranteed uh
granted i should say an insurer is able
to be monitored against those standards
this reduces the need for consumers to
make complex inquiries
regarding an insurance financial
strength and under indicators
and this is a very important piece of
the legislation because what has
happened in the past
is ordinary hard-working new zealanders
have actually not had the financial
ability to wade through
complex prospectuses and financial
statements to determine
for themselves whether an insurance or
company
or any sort of organization is in fact
meeting the requirements necessary for
sound investment
this licensing arrangement monitored by
the reserve bank
actually puts that in place therefore
protecting new zealanders
to a large extent insurers covered by
the new regime
will need to be licensed before the bill
comes into force and the bill will come
into effect 18 months after
it has received royal assent after this
date it will be an offence to carry on
or hold out that you carry on insurance
business in new zealand without a
license
this is why i say mr speaker that a high
level of certainty
has been granted to the new zealand
public as a result of this bill
there are other important parts in this
bill as well risk management
requirements
fit and proper requirements for example
require
insurers will be required to consider
qualifications background experience
of key personnel this lines up with
another bill we passed in this house
regulating the financial
services sector statutory fund
separation for life insurance and
similar long-term insurance funds
capital adequacy and solution standards
and appropriate financial regulatory
reporting
again most important to all new
zealanders
to ensure that they can have confidence
in this sector ensure
credit ratings what i've talked about
before a supervision framework including
effective
distress management provisions
mr speaker as i outlined there are three
reasons why i support this bill and
three reasons
why labor supports this bill this bill
is another step in achieving clear
robust laws and regulations
across the financial sector we do not
want to see ever again the carnage that
was wrought
by this last financial recession
secondly mr speaker this bill will
provide a much higher level of security
for new zealanders
with exposure and investment in the
insurance industry
and finally the third reason is
important
because it tidies up legislation around
the sector where there was an
unacceptable level of uncertainty
for both the sector itself and for new
zealanders
as a result of this i commend this bill
to this house thank you
sam lotto thank you mr speaker
mr speaker i rise